[musical swirl]
[electric chimes]
[orchestra tuning]
Watch Online Movies and Series for FREE
www.osdb.link/lm
[soft music]
[muffled sounds]
[music swells]
[birds chirping]
[soft snoring]
[distant Indian
war whoops and gunfire]
[canon fire and yelling]
[cannon fire booms]
[gasping]
[cacophony of
gunfire and yelling]
[horse neighs]
Where is the General?
Where is he?
Where is Braddock?
[gun cocks]
What happened?
We've been ambushed!
From where?
Over the hill!
[panting]
[sounds muffle.
gasping as ringing starts]
[grunts. sounds returning]
[dramatic music]
[cannon fire booms]
[dramatic music intensifies]
[coughing]
I wouldn't bother. Washington.
The battle is lost.
Where is the General?
Ordered a full retreat.
That way lies nothing but death.
And my men?
You have no men.
The Virginians.
They were at
the front of the line.
If you go that way.
you will die.
You look like death already.
Listen to me.
You'll never find them.
and even if you did.
you'd never make it back.
[cannon fire booms]
Washington.
Washington!
Come. my friend.
What could be worth the risk?
[dramatic stinger]
[solemn music]
[solemn music continues]
-[Lawrence] Mary.
I'm so sorry.
This must be Jack.
This is...our Jack
[Mary whispers to baby]
Where is he?
He's there.
He’s not spoken since...
[Mary] since his father died.
[solemn music continues]
Hello. George.
Do you remember me?
I'm your half-brother.
Lawrence.
You're an officer?
I was. yes.
Captain in his Majesty's Navy.
I have something for you.
It’s a surveyor’s compass.
It measures distances
of land and sea.
This was our father's.
And now it's yours.
Won’t you need it?
Well. my next adventure is
here with you. George.
I have been appointed Adjutant
General of the Virginia militia.
So. you will command soldiers?
I'm to organize militia.
Volunteers. really.
[wagon wheels rumbling]
[mournful music plays]
[George] Do Washington
men die young?
[Lawrence] What?
[George] I heard them say
Washington men die young.
That it's a curse to our name.
Is that true?
Are you afraid to die?
[George] Mother says I will
not be going back to school.
[Lawrence] There's nothing
wrong with tenant farming.
It's an honorable profession.
[George] But that is not
what I want.
[Lawrence] It's what
duty demands.
Time and circumstance
have changed.
William Fairfax
is attending school.
Why can I not?
The Fairfaxes
are of a superior class.
With advantages we
will never possess. George.
The world is
often an unfair place.
And you must take what
it gives you and make it yours.
Now come inside.
[bright music plays]
George. where are you going?
To school!
Stubborn child.
[Lawrence] It's two miles.
I know.
They will not let you in.
[George] They will.
[axe thuds]
Don't take it out on the tree.
George. Stop. stop!
[Mary sighs]
They turned me away.
Because of you.
And now I have nothing.
Nothing?
[scoffs]
We have 250 acres.
Ten slaves in bondage
to feed.
And one widow's purse.
near empty.
You're the eldest son
in this house.
and you have
a duty to it.
That is not what I want.
I want more than this.
And I want a husband.
back from his fever.
Providence denied me this.
Then Providence is cruel!
God raises
what is well grounded.
You'll not abandon
what is yours. nor will I.
You're my son.
and a Washington.
and you'll behave like both.
[Mary sighs deeply]
[sighs]
[door creaks open]
[Lawrence breathes deeply]
Here.
Rules of Civility
and Decent Behavior.
That will teach you
how to be a proper gentleman.
Then Cato. Plutarch.
Essential readings.
Seneca and Cincinnatus.
If one desires to be great.
he must study those that were.
It’s a lot of books. I know--
I am sorry for
your misfortune. George.
If no one else will
teach you. I'll teach you.
But I could loan you these.
one by one.
if you do your chores.
[bright music]
[Lawrence] “Every public
action should” what?
[George] “Show respect to
those who are present.”
What do you
think respect means?
[George] To listen to or obey
the one you are respecting.
[Lawrence] Perhaps.
But obedience can be commanded.
Respect must be earned.
That is why I became a soldier.
[bright music continues]
Aristocracy is a game. George.
But. you could learn
to play it. I suppose.
What piece are we?
We are pawns. George.
But even a pawn can take a king.
Play again?
Yeah.
Up.
[Lawrence] Very nice. George.
[Lawrence] Remember. heels down.
chest up.
I think it's
now time you ride alone.
Wouldn't you agree?
Yes.
Very well.
Go on then.
[adventurous music]
[Lawrence] Not too fast now.
Steady.
[young George] “To obtain
the applause of
deserving men
is a heartfelt satisfaction...”
[adventurous music swells]
[George] “...to merit them
is my highest wish...”
[indistinct chatter]
[Col. Gooch] So. here he is.
The boy who
writes all the letters...
petitioning for a
‘royal’ commission?
Yes. sir.
I dream of
becoming a British officer.
Ensign or lieutenant.
as his Majesty sees fit.
I believe my brother
communicated this on my behalf.
Lawrence Washington.
He served under the--
If I were to allow it...
the purchase price
for an ensigncy in the
Coldstreams is £700.
Do you possess that. sir?
No. sir. I do not.
Then why not
seek to join the militia?
Well. I wish to serve
the Crown as an actual officer.
Then how much
land do you possess?
I am a custodian. um.
under my brother's estate
at Mount Vernon.
Tenant farmer.
Education?
I received no formal schooling
after my father died. sir.
But I recently obtained
my surveyor's license.
To be a British officer.
you must first be a gentleman.
If I may. sir. how is it that my
brother qualified yet I do not?
He owns Mount Vernon.
He was properly
educated in England.
And what's more.
he's married to a Fairfax.
Yes. and he has
been a great mentor to me.
I-I've studied
to become a gentleman.
I've even compiled
all I've learned.
Goodness. man.
how much do you write?
Well. I've compiled
it from other books.
It's called Rules of
Civility and Decent Behaviour.
Which is to say
you plagiarised it.
No. No. no--
Well. yes. but. err...
Imitation of great men
does not make you one.
I... I ask again. sir.
How may I become a
British officer of the Crown?
-You cannot--
-There must be a path.
There is not for you.
And please.
stop writing me letters.
Go!
[dramatic music]
[George] Hello. Jack.
Good to see you.
Are you an officer now?
Not yet.
But someday.
[Mary] Or never.
If God hears my prayers.
“Be not tedious in discourse.”
[exhales]
Especially tonight.
[distant footfalls]
Where are you off to?
To see Lawrence.
At Belvoir? You're not invited.
How do you expect to get in?
Is it a sin to seek advancement?
It is to them.
You're just a pawn to them.
Well. even a pawn
can take a king.
[noble fanfare]
[classical music plays]
[Steward] Invitation. sir.
I am Mr. Washington. uh.
George Washington.
Half-brother to Lawrence.
who is married to Anne.
formerly Fairfax.
Thank you for the genealogy.
Now. your invitation. sir?
Ah.
Um...I don't have it.
The guests for this party
have been chosen
with great specificity.
so I suggest you find it.
Mr. Washington.
Sir.
Ah...
-Good evening.
-Thank you.
[curious music]
[laughter]
Good evening.
-Good evening.
-Evening. sir.
We need more ice.
Uh. can I. can I carry
that upstairs?
Uh. no need. sir.
How-how do I get in
the house?
[string music plays]
[woman] You don't
belong here.
Clever entrance. though.
Most guests just
enter through the front door.
My brother spoke to
me of this gathering. He is--
Married to Ann Fairfax.
Yes. I know.
You. on the
other hand. are not.
A child of one of Virginia's
largest fortunes and
family estates?
You're right. I'm not.
And you were right. I'm rich.
But...
I also don't feel
like I belong.
Well. that's like saying a rose
doesn't belong in a garden.
I'll take that compliment.
I'd be happy
if there were more.
Here's the problem with
trying to sneak into a party.
You. sir. stand out in a crowd.
Then dance with me.
I only dance
with invited guests.
Well. perhaps you should make
room for someone truly worthy.
Because. I don’t see anyone
like that here.
Mr. Washington. aren't you bold?
Well. I'm off.
To where?
To fulfill my solemn duty.
Charm.
[Lawrence] Gently does it.
George.
Best to proceed with caution.
It would profit Sally's
family greatly
if she were to
marry a Fairfax.
Like you did?
[Lawrence chuckles]
Yes.
And until I did. I held all my
hopes very loosely.
The odds were against me.
Well. the odds
have always been against us.
Wish me luck.
Good luck.
[indistinct conversation]
William. Thank you for
having me in your home.
George. what a surprise.
I didn't expect to
see you in a place like this.
How ever did you get in?
I was enticed by the
promise of beautiful women.
Well. we'd
hate to disappoint you.
You haven't.
Meet Thomas Gage.
Newly minted Major.
recently arrived from London
by order of the Crown.
Pleasure.
Pleasure is mine.
I. too. one day
hope to serve His Majesty.
Tell me. Washington.
what is your opinion
of the French
building forts on our land?
Well. I think the Ohio
is a frontier.
It belongs to the one
who tames it.
-[William] Ah.
-Well said.
But in reality. it belongs to
the one who buys it.
That is the way
of things. is it not?
[a minuet begins to play]
Ah. a minuet.
I love a minuet.
I believe I have the first
dance. if you'll excuse us.
Pleasure to meet you.
I hope we meet again.
Pleasure.
-Where are you off to?
-Sally.
My solemn duty.
[deep sigh]
Ah!
Lord Fairfax.
Begging your pardon.
I've dreamed of
seeing your library.
These are my true tenants.
Who are you?
George Washington. sir.
Brother to Lawrence.
I didn't know he'd invited you.
Neither did he.
if you must know.
Ah! So. I've caught
you slipping in.
And you...
caught me slipping out. Come.
I can't take much
of these soirées.
So. I hide.
Until my wife finds me
and rousts me back out.
"When vice prevails. and
impious men bear sway.
the post of
honor is a private station."
Cato.
You've seen the play?
No. but I've read it
50 times over.
"Tis not in mortals
to command success.
But we'll do more.
We'll deserve it."
Well said. [chuckles]
Do you happen to
have Pope's Essay on Man?
Would it be imposing if I
asked to borrow it?
I obtained a letter of
introduction from your cousin.
An eccentric fellow. isn't he?
Indeed he is.
He lent me a book on surveying
from his library.
Not nearly as grand as yours.
I put it to good use
and obtained my license.
I know you own
five million acres now.
The only thing
a landowner ever desires...
is the plot next to his.
Yes. I do.
I also know a
great amount of that land
is in the Ohio Valley
and has not been charted.
I sense a looming storm
over the Ohio Territory.
Inevitable. I'm afraid.
I could go there.
Survey it and map it for you.
A land that isn't
properly measured
cannot be properly valued.
or protected.
Much of that
territory is unexplored.
Many have traveled there.
never to be seen again.
Yes.
But no man who
lived a life of ease
ever left a name
worth remembering. sir.
I'll take the risk upon myself.
I'll make it to the furthest
reaches of your
plot and report back.
And I'll put my name
to that promise.
Is this man bothering you. sir?
Hardly.
I accept your proposal. George.
Thank you. sir.
[spirited. upbeat music]
Enjoy the party. Washington.
[indistinct chatter]
[man] Get out of the way.
Christopher Gist.
George?
George.
Good to see you.
It's good to see you.
George. these are the brothers
Frisk. Henry. the oldest.
And his baby brother. David.
[Christopher] My two
most loyal friends.
Do not trust them.
[laughs]
That's a nice coat
you got there.
Careful! He's a thief!
Shut your--
Leave him alone!
Where are you
coming from. all...
fresh and plucked?
Belvoir.
[mockingly] Ooh!
That mean you too fancy to. uh.
place a little wager?
How bout you place one for me?
[laughs]
Oh. I like him.
What are you doing here?
I have a job for us.
I'm too drunk for work.
Ambition waits for no man.
What is it?
Surveying the Ohio territory.
I need someone who can
keep me alive.
For who?
Lord Fairfax.
What part?
Most all of it.
He pays by the acre.
[Henry laughs]
Well...
let's get it done.
[laughs]
To Virginia!
[spirited. upbeat
music continues]
That is the last time.
Henry!
David!
[incoherent yelling]
She's your mother. too!
Yeah. we don't
know that for sure.
[men yelling fades out]
[adventurous music]
[George] It's beautiful.
isn't it?
Yeah.
But it don't belong to you.
Well. if we go far enough.
it doesn't belong to anyone.
[George] Dear madam.
Gazing at the new world.
I now write to express my joy.
I was honored with
your short
but very agreeable favor
of our first acquaintance.
In this case.
the one who is too sensible of
her charms to deny the power.
whose influence I feel
and must ever submit to.
I am aware of
how impossible this is. But...
if you will allow me
to prove myself.
I pledge to rule out
all disappointment.
I wish I could be with you.
Or rather. you here with me.
So you could witness the
beauty of this land.
Let's see who this is.
Pass it-- pass it back.
Pass it back.
Miss Sally Cary?
You might as well petition the
Queen of England. George.
She's above your station.
Permanently.
Fight battles you can win.
George.
Nice signature. though.
“I am your humble
devoted servant”.
[rushing water]
[horse neighing]
[Christopher] We're not
going to make it back
before winter sets in.
[George] The horses
have done all they can.
We must leave them.
There’s a village.
about a half a day’s
journey from here.
We could shelter.
Ride out the cold.
No. no. that's too long a time.
[shivering] I suppose you'd
rather freeze to death.
We have to return.
So you can see your
woman?
So we can get paid.
It’s unbecoming of a gentleman
to lie to himself.
[whistles]
[ominous music]
[Christopher speaks Seneca]
[speaking Seneca]
He's not too
fond of your compass.
Offer them the horses.
George?
They’re no longer
of use to us...
but they could still be
saved to serve them.
You offer dying horses?
For the land
given to me by my father?
To him by his father?
Hey... hey.
You have no right to take
what we possess for generations.
We are not here
to claim this land.
We are surveyors only.
I know what
you want. Englishman.
And I offer something
more.
Something for your king.
[dramatic music]
Whose fort is that?
The French.
[dramatic music continues]
[Christopher] Are you
sure
this is the fastest way home?
[George] Saves us two days.
[Christopher] If we fall off
this raft.
we'll freeze to death.
No. no. We have to get
this information back.
[grunts]
You're full of
surprises. you know.
Speaking their tongue?
Well...”know thy enemy.”
Are they the enemy?
They let us go.
Only because they hate
the French more than--
More than they hate us.
George.
George. look!
Look. look.
Get to the shore!
[both grunt with effort]
Push!
I'm trying.
Get to the shore!
The current is too strong.
No.
Christopher...
Hold on. hold on.
[both yell]
[music intensifies]
[gasps]
[George] Swim!
[Christopher] The maps!
[George] Christopher!
[dramatic music]
Did you get the maps?
[grunts]
[both shivering]
George. you think
you could swim across?
[grunts]
Stay awake. George.
Save your strength.
Christopher.
Christopher. wake up.
Wake up!
Christopher!
[Christopher breathes
raggedly]
You believe in miracles?
Get up.
How did it freeze?
Do we risk it?
[gasps]
[Lawrence coughs]
You can confirm this?
Yes.
So can Christopher Gist.
[coughs]
If you have these delivered to
Governor Dinwiddie. he can...
Consumption.
They say.
[Lawrence coughs]
All men die. George.
I can't go to the governor
in my state.
[coughs]
You wish to
advance your station?
My condition
may be your answer.
[coughs]
[church bells toll]
[indistinct chatter]
You saw these
things with your own eyes.
Yes. Your Excellency.
On land owned
rightly and duly by us --
Well. the-- the Fairfaxes.
I also own a significant
share of land there.
This French encroachment
cannot stand.
They must be told
to abandon it.
By whom. sir? We don't
even know where they are.
I do. sir.
I could lead this expedition.
To deliver your demands
to the French.
I know the land. sir.
better than anyone.
You?
In the 15 years since the
Crown sent me to serve.
I've yet to have a good
experience with a...colonist.
Well. I look forward
to changing your opinion.
If there used to be a
colonial expedition.
it would be led
by your own brother.
He commands the militia.
Lawrences health fails him. sir.
And he is no longer able to
fulfill the duties of his post.
Here.
He recommends me
as his replacement.
So you have ambition?
Yes. sir. I do.
I see you met the savage
we call the Half-King.
I have met the man.
He led me to this information.
but...
whether he can be trusted...
I’m not certain.
I should be
alarmed if you were.
Go and parley with
this Half-King.
learn all you can from him.
Then take your men
to Fort LeBoeuf.
demand the French leave.
My...my...my men. sir?
Yes. Recruit 150
of your fellow Virginians.
Lead them and
deliver this message.
Which says what. sir?
That they leave immediately.
And if the French refuse?
Do not permit them to refuse.
So. then I am to fight?
You are to deliver a message
and await further orders.
[Gage] Your Excellency.
if I may.
Will he not need the assistance
of professional soldiers
of the Crown?
No. militia will do. Especially
under one of such ambition.
You shall receive the rank of
Major in the Virginia militia.
which is not a
royal commission. understood?
Mmm.
There is an interpreter here.
Van Braam. Dutchman. Take him.
Will my men and
I receive equal pay. sir?
To whom?
British officers of the Crown.
Mr. Washington. you've just
advanced from farmer
to Major in a
matter of seconds.
What you ask for is
offensive to me.
Then I will
volunteer my service.
I have no need
to pay that is not equal
to those of whom
I will prove myself equal.
Sir.
God save the King.
[uplifting music]
[Sally] I can't say
red becomes you. George.
You don't think so?
Well. even if I did.
I wouldn't say.
[Sally] Thank you for
your letters.
I read them all ten times over.
At the river's fork. the world
widened as though God himself
had drawn back the curtain
and whispered. "Begin."
These are not surveyor’s notes.
No. You love the frontier the
way poets love their first muse.
Why?
It loved me first. I guess.
Offered fairness.
Fairness?
Yes. Because the frontier is
new. wild. unclaimed.
Vast enough to outrun
the old ways.
And old rules? Like dowries and
fathers who barter daughters.
Rules that say a man is measured
by ancestors you never met.
Do you ever fear of
choosing incorrectly?
That the path you seek might
vanish if you hesitate?
The fear of not being able
to choose is worse.
My fear is choosing.
Then being told it was never
my choice to begin with.
Then what would your choice be?
If we were to follow
the river west. just you and I.
what would we call that life?
Wild. Beautiful.
Dangerous. But. but free.
I yearn for the
courage I see in you.
And I. for the grace
you carry with ease.
I should be getting back.
Where?
Another party.
Another performance.
My solemn duty.
[romantic music]
[adventurous music]
Congratulations on your first
command. Major.
An army of outlaws.
debtors. slaves. and...
[chuckles] well. patriots.
Got any rum in
those carts?
Only what’s rationed.
Well. then ration us some.
Back in line. Frisk.
[Henry] Ain't no line.
That snake trail is
the best we can do.
It ain’t wide enough
for the carts.
We should leave ‘em.
Then how would we carry the rum?
Fair point.
Tucker!
Yes. sir.
We’ll camp here for the night.
Ride ahead.
Make sure the road is clear.
[Christopher] I wake
up at midnight.
George is staring
into the woods.
Propped against a tree.
musket in his lap.
He says he's
been keepin' watch.
You scared of the dark. George?
George. you remember?
[men laugh]
Another love letter.
[laughing]
[Christopher] That woman's
gonna make you soft.
[horse neighs]
It's Tucker's horse.
[muskets cracking]
Van Braam.
What business do you have with us?
We have no conflict with you.
We are only here...
To speak to the French.
We meet again.
I'm Tanacharison.
Of the Seneca nation.
You ride on land we call home.
The Governor assures
me you're willing to aid us.
Many Indians are aligned
with the French. Why aren't you?
I know their nature.
And their intentions.
What are yours?
To demand they leave.
And when they do not?
That's not my decision.
And yet you are here.
Yes. and I would
greatly appreciate
any help you
could give us.
What are you called?
George.
Major George Washington.
The French fort is
a day from here.
We can take you.
[ominous music]
Why are you here?
Why do you hate them?
When I was a child
I was taken captive by the French
[horse neighing]
I watched them boil my father.
And eat him.
From the royal Governor of Virginia:
Sir. the lands upon the Ohio River
are notoriously known
to be the property
of the Crown of Great Britain
that it is a matter of equal concern
and surprise to hear that a body of
French forces are erecting fortresses
within His Majesty's dominions.
His dominion?
Continue.
In the name of the King. my master.
I have sent the bearer hereof.
Major George Washington.
one of the Adjutants-General
of this British Dominion.
You are the Major?
or his aide?
I am Major Washington.
[speaking French]
[men laugh]
He's inviting
us to dine with them.
[ominous music]
Can we speak in private?
[speaking French]
He says there's no
need to leave the table.
We are all friends here.
[Christopher speaking
Seneca]
Know thy enemy indeed.
So. how is it you are a Major?
Do you even shave?
[men laugh]
You have no military service.
Is it true?
Magnifique.
You are not British.
yet they send you
to speak for them.
Why do you think that is?
So that when you fail.
they'll have someone to blame.
The King emphatically demands
you leave the Ohio country.
and the territories altogether.
This land has long been
claimed by the British Crown.
And when was this?
[in French] When?
When did they claim it?
You must withdraw.
Because you
think you own this land?
Who does own this land.
if not the one who has
the will to tame it?
[fists banging on the table]
[indistinct chatter]
I accept your message.
You have delivered it.
Now go.
The King demands a reply.
Then tell your King
we have claimed it.
We will never leave.
Then we will force you to leave.
Oh.
You do not want to start a war.
Take your pet savage and go.
[tense music]
[George] Camp 15 miles
south of here.
I’m going to ride ahead
and deliver the message.
Should we send a scout?
I'm the fastest scout we have.
[ominous music]
[door opens]
Major.
You will deliver
this ultimatum at once.
The French spit in my face.
Governor. with respect.
could you clarify--
Transcribe all you have.
so I can report this
to the council in the morning.
Very well.
Grant me one night’s rest
and fresh mounts.
I’ve ridden
300 miles to--
You will rest when
His Majesty's frontier rests.
Before dawn. you'll present a
full transcription
of your journal.
Maps. strength estimates.
every scratch of observation.
for the council's brief
at ten o'clock. Understood?
Understood. sir.
Good.
Now go and prove
the Crown correct
in placing
trust in a provincial.
This is a dangerous escalation.
George.
You are to deliver this?
I've been ordered
to deliver this.
You volunteered.
No.
- No. perhaps I can speak--
- No. no.
This is the moment
I've been waiting for.
I don't think it is. George.
Why has no one else volunteered?
Why does no British
officer lead this expedition?
They’re using you. George.
As a proxy.
To claim land for them.
If you succeed.
they will rob you of the glory.
If you fail. they'll have
a colonial to blame.
Then I will not fail.
If you do.
it could start a war.
Thank you for your trust in me.
That's not what I meant.
I will claim it. and
I will earn their respect.
That is what you
taught me. is it not?
Besides. this is a new world.
A new world?
The soil may be new.
but it’s owners still write
their ledgers in old ink.
Let them write.
You're betting your life on a
system designed to deny you.
Every triumph you have
will be chalked up to luck.
or the Native allies
or the British themselves.
Never you.
So I should stay here.
mind the crops and live quietly
because I was born quietly?
Do nothing with my life?
Better alive and quiet
than dead and forgotten
in the Alleghenies.
You sound like mother.
I speak the truth.
[laughs] Well I would rather die
unknown than live
believing the world’s
measure of me is fixed.
That...that is pride.
No. that is faith in what a man
can forge with his own hands.
You cannot forge
your way into their system.
And why not?
Because that is not
the way the world works.
Then someone should remake it.
[Lawrence coughs]
George. you
cannot change these things.
You may well die trying.
George--
I wish you believed in me.
[coughing]
[soft string music]
[indistinct chatter]
[Sally] Major Washington.
I thought you were leading
your men to the frontier.
Tomorrow I am.
But I have returned
on an urgent matter.
I'll go back in the morning.
But. tonight. I am here for you.
[inaudible whispers]
George. there is no
fairness here.
Miss Cary—may I
have this dance?
[string music plays]
Yes. Major.
George. I see
you found a tailor.
Yes.
Tonight I wear
His Majesty's commission.
At dawn. I am
to lead 150 soldiers
to demand the
French leave our land.
Well. our land. to be precise.
And this is not exactly
His Majesty's commission.
Your uniform. however.
crimson. still prints colonial.
William.
It is a point I make
intentionally. Sally.
I fear for you. George.
And I question
our Governor's decision.
If the situation
with the French is so dire.
why would they not
send professional
soldiers of the Crown?
Because I volunteered.
And if you care so much.
why didn't you?
Because I have an estate to run.
And I have a fortune to manage.
And people depend on me.
But...
I can send along two of
my best slaves. Charles and Sam.
Charles knows horses better than
most grooms in Virginia.
Well. I wouldn't want
to deprive you of their labor.
We have plenty.
[Lord Fairfax] Major
Washington.
Congratulations on
your rank and assignment.
An astonishing rise.
Thank you. sir.
So. what think you of our young
William and Sally?
Yes.
Do they not make a.
a handsome couple?
We are gathered
here to celebrate this.
Their betrothal
is scarcely a week old.
Uh...
Indeed they do.
Splendid!
Now. may I propose a toast?
To Major Washington—
who rides at first light...
[speech fades behind music]
[low rumbling sound]
[Fairfax] Major Washington.
William. Miss Cary.
Forgive the stir.
I look forward to returning
worthy of your investment...
and your care.
[soft music]
[George] Act on the defensive
But if any attempts are made to
disrupt our work or settlements.
restrain all such offenders.
and make prisoners of.
or kill and destroy. them.
Well. that’s clear as mud.
He cannot be serious.
“Destroy them?”
If it’s war he wants.
it's best to reinforce us
with proper British soldiers.
We ain't here to fight.
Then why are you?
To get paid.
This is our duty.
No. it ain't.
We delivered his little letter.
We should leave.
You will not.
Or I will have
you flogged as a deserter.
Now. we didn't
sign up for no war.
You put on the coat!
You took an oath.
You have a duty. as do I.
If this goes wrong.
he’ll blame Virginia.
[George] Dinwiddie speaks
for the Crown.
It's decided. This is a direct
order and we will obey it.
It's not direct at all.
Then your gods have
delivered you to war.
It is not our intent.
[Tucker] I found
their encampment.
It’s much further south.
Much closer.
How close?
Five miles.
[Tanacharison] He searches for
land to build another fort.
To demand you abandon
the land he calls his own.
Take me to him.
A simple
reconnaissance. Agreed?
[tense music]
[Tanacharison] Drunk with
his own pride.
He defies you and your King
by traveling this far.
What will you do?
Hold your ground.
I'll tell them once
again to leave.
What will you do
when they refuse?
-Pray they--
-[gunshot]
Who fired that shot?
[gunshot]
Hold your ground!
[yelling in French]
[indian whoops and yells]
[gunshots]
[yelling in French]
Forward!
[yelling]
[gunshots]
Hold your fire!
Prisoners only!
Prisoners--
[yelling]
[gunshot]
[sigh]
[sound of heartbeat]
[soldier yells]
[yelling]
[gunshots]
We should have killed everyone of you.
Thou art not yet dead. my father.
-Wait!
-[Jumonville groans]
Wait!
[indian whoops and cheers]
[George] I do not know who
fired that first shot.
but in light of
these unfortunate events.
I fear a war with the
French is indeed imminent.
We are building a fort and
taking up a defensive position.
In the spirit
of mutual benefit.
please send reinforcements
to aid our endeavor.
[David] Hey.
why don't we arm them?
We need all the men we can get.
They might shoot us.
Wouldn't you?
Fair point.
-Gist!
-Yep.
Permission to speak my mind.
Never stopped you?
[sarcastic laugh]
Building this fort too low.
What do you mean?
The walls?
No. not the walls--
This here. this is a
dry lake bed.
One good rain. it’ll flood out.
Besides. I could shoot
every one of us from them trees.
Major know what he’s doin?
What you writing?
Another plea for reinforcements.
From who?
Colonies.
Pennsylvania don't care
about Virginia's problems.
The French are the
concern of all. Agreed?
This area lies awfully low.
The forest gives us cover.
The great meadows offer
plenty of space
and a clear view
of any oncoming threats.
If they attack.
it'll be from the front.
Or. we'll be easy
targets. when the fort floods.
Well. Gist. what would
you have me do?
Major Washington.
The King's troops.
What about them?
[Tucker] They're here.
Where's Washington?
I am Major Washington.
[scoffs]
Captain James Mackay.
Orders from Governor Dinwiddie.
We are here to reinforce
the Virginia Regiment
and deal with this...
situation you’ve created.
French and Indian soldiers.
Professional soldiers.
Are nearly upon us.
Over a thousand in total.
They are commanded by
Louis Coulon de Villiers.
Brother to Joseph Coulon
de Villiers de Jumonville.
The man who you killed.
This letter says Colonel
Joshua Fry is in command.
Oh. the boy can read.
Where is he?
Dead.
Fell from his horse two
days ago and broke his neck.
You are to assume his rank
as Colonel. Mr. Washington.
[George] Well then. welcome.
We need all
the help we can get.
I do not take orders from you.
But...
you said I was to
assume the rank is Colonel.
My commission is royal.
You could be a general and I
wouldn't have to listen to you.
Praise God.
Now. what do
you call this... fort?
Well. it was made by necessity.
So I think
that's a fitting name.
Mmm.
We will camp 100 yards
to the front.
No doubt the French
will engage us there.
Colonel.
Van Braam.
[Mackay] The boy can read.
[Mackay chuckles]
[water splashing]
[thunder booms]
How's the progress?
Ditch is taking in water
faster than we can throw it.
I say. this keeps up.
I’ll commission my men to
construct a Royal Navy.
Keep trying.
I could shoot you
from the trees.
The French won’t fire
They’ll assemble in open fields.
To fight with honor.
You call this
land the New World?
Yet you live by the old ways.
They will lead you to death.
Any recruits among the Shawnee?
No.
What about the Delaware
or the Mingo?
No. Some have
even joined the French.
None will aid you.
Neither will we.
You will not leave!
Your vengeance started this.
And your stubbornness
will be the end of it.
The French are cowards.
The British are fools.
You do not
know how to fight here.
I was born here on
this land. as were you.
Can we not
fight for it together?
This land
does not belong to you.
While you kill each other.
we wait to reclaim it.
[Christopher] George. you made
the wrong choice of ground.
Admit it. That's it. It's
alright. it's alright. Admit it.
Our supplies are exhausted.
We’ve two days' rations at best.
Move camp and save the men.
We will stand our ground.
Any sign of the French?
Nothing. No doubt the arrival
of actual soldiers
put a stop
to their advancements.
But listen. my men are
camping in what is now a swamp.
What do you want me to do?
Find solid ground.
Or better yet. an
experienced commander.
Are you
challenging my authority?
[scoffs] You have no authority.
-[gunshot]
-[Mackay grunts]
Trees! They're in the trees!
Take cover!
-[horse neighs]
-[gunshots boom]
[yelling and gunshots]
Move. move.
Go. go. go.
Grab a musket.
Move. move. move. move!
[George] Hold the line.
Form a line on me.
A line? Yeah. a smart idea.
Fire!
They’re firing from all sides.
To the front with me!
Form up! On me. on me.
Christopher.
Yeah?
Divide the men. Keep 50 in
the fort and fire to the trees.
50 won’t fit in the fort.
it’s flooded out.
As many as you can. then.
All right men on me!
Move. move. move. move.
Everyone to the front line.
Present.
Fire!
[Henry] George. cannons!
[David] George.
what's the plan. here?
Second rank!
Forward!
Present!
Make ready!
Fire!
[bullets whizzing]
[men yell]
Retreat!
Back to the fort.
Back to the fort. Get inside!
[George] Move!
Get inside! Get inside!
[men yelling]
Come on. Get in!
Get in there!
[George] Get inside!
Inside!
[Christopher] George!
George!
[George] Barricade the door!
[George] Hold!
-[cannon fire booms]
-[men yelling]
[Henry] Powder’s wet.
Nothing's firin'!
We’re sittin’ ducks here.
Colonel.
We keep fighting!
Attach bayonets!
The battle is lost.
The battle is just begun.
George!
Man your post!
Man your posts!
Washington!
Save your men!
I will not
surrender my first command.
Advance troops!
They're coming in.
Man your posts!
Hold. hold. hold!
[Christopher grunts]
Gist!
Just breathe. just breathe.
Hey. hey.
You're gonna be okay.
Breathe. breathe.
breathe. I'm sorry.
[sound muffles
behind music]
Major!
Yes.
[George] Surrender.
[solemn music]
I'm sorry. Christopher.
I am so sorry!
[Jacob] Washington.
Terms are somewhat favorable.
It's a mutual withdrawal.
They take our artillery.
we'll remove the flag.
And also they demand
you take responsibility
for their commander's
unfortunate death.
We didn't start this.
Nobody knows
who fired that first shot.
I've offered myself as security.
I will go with them.
This is the best
possible outcome. Colonel.
Colonel.
What is the date today?
July third.
July the third will be
etched in my memory forever.
[solemn music]
I'm so sorry.
I'm so. so sorry.
[Dinwiddie]
Assassination.
You confessed to assassinating
a French Officer!
It was not my intention.
Your Excellency.
Is this not your signature?
Our intention had
never been to trouble peace.
but only to revenge
the assassination of
one of our officers.
The translator failed me. sir.
I didn't realize.
I thought that--
Washington.
To lead is to forfeit
the right to make excuses.
Have you any
idea what you've done?
You've started a war!
[slams desk]
I'll report that
the battle was lost
due to poor munitions
and lack of supplies.
But that is not the truth. sir.
That is the truth
that suits me. otherwise--
Sir. I came here
to resign my commission.
I am not fit to lead.
I was never fit to lead.
God save the King.
And your resignation would
say that I'm not fit to choose.
Washington. you
abandon this office.
you abandon your
ambition with it.
Understood. sir.
Where's Lawrence?
I'm sorry.
[screams]
He wanted you
to have his journals.
You were right.
You knew I would fail.
It's not your fault. George.
You did not lay your
brother low. Nor those men.
I chose the ground.
I put on the coat.
I gave the order.
And now
because of that...
Good men are dead.
When your father died.
there were accounts
I could not read.
acres I could not plow.
But I learned. as women do.
to keep a tally with one hand
and a prayer with the other.
I hardened because
the wind here is hard.
Put iron in my voice.
I was hard on you. George.
I see you learned
to be hard on yourself.
That was my sin.
You said Providence
placed me here.
Why?
For me to fail?
Perhaps.
Failure is
the tutor sent by God.
If you don't learn from it.
you've failed twice.
If you do learn from it.
you've earned wisdom.
So...
What did it tell you?
To go back.
But I'm afraid...
of making the same mistakes.
War is not the path I would
choose for you. But...
Oh...
On your feet. son.
If you must
return to soldiering. go.
As God's servant.
Do it with your whole heart.
Find your path.
Make it yours.
Make it straight.
And prove them wrong.
Because even a
pawn can take the king.
[dramatic music]
[drum beat plays]
I'm sorry to disturb. sir.
I am George Washington.
Ah!
The reason I am here.
Meet Colonel Thomas Gage.
Gage has recently
been promoted to colonel
by Royal Commission.
We’ve met.
I'm assuming you
seek your previous command.
Gage has been tasked
with leading your militia
and is far more qualified.
I'm sure he is.
I neither ask for rank nor pay.
I'm here to volunteer
as your aide-de-camp.
I believe I could be
of some assistance to you.
Oh. do not worry.
Young Washington. These uh.
these French and their savages
may have been a formidable enemy
to you and your militia.
but to the King's troops. they
are more of a nuisance. really.
Bit of a waste of powder.
We will prevail. With ease.
But with all due respect. sir.
I do not think
it will be with ease.
-Having fought--
-And lost.
Having fought
within the region. sir.
I believe I could
be of some help to you.
Fort Duquesne is difficult.
Duquesne can hardly detain me
above three or four days.
Sir. this is a very
different type of battle.
Just the trip to the fort
alone is treach--
A week at most.
A month.
A month?
If lucky.
For most of the journey.
you'll be
traveling a single file.
over what is barely a trail.
Not even wide enough for wagons.
I've surveyed the land.
I know this land.
The French are located here.
where the three rivers meet.
Because of the land. the style
of warfare is. uh.
it's different.
These are not the
open battlefields
to which you're accustomed.
I have fought on
a great many battlefields.
Not in the new world. sir.
You lost in the new world.
Yes.
You're right.
But failure is a great teacher.
I desire to serve under
someone of your ability
and experience to learn more.
Sir.
You may come. As advisor
and aide. That is all.
Thank you. General Braddock.
Colonel Gage see
that he is accommodated.
Yes. sir.
[drum beat plays]
[Braddock] What is the delay?
Move these wagons.
So. Washington.
From colonel to aide-de-camp.
How the mighty have fallen.
Well. I was never given
the Royal Commission as colonel.
so did it truly matter?
This is important to you?
Fairness? Yes.
Gage. what on
God's earth is the delay here?
Fallen tree. I believe. sir.
Well. how-how do you expect
to win a battle
if you can't
even defeat a tree?
Yes. sir.
I have fought the King's battles
on three continents.
but never have I
been defeated by a tree.
[Braddock] This is no army.
This is a centipede with gout.
[Tucker] Henry. David.
Look who's here.
Major?
Aide-de-camp.
It seems you're my
superiors. actually.
Take up an axe
and help us with this tree.
Gladly.
[Gage] What seems to
be the delay?
I'm sorry. Colonel.
There's no damn road.
That's the delay.
[Gage] Washington.
these are your friends?
Why do they not wear
the King’s red?
Or at least try?
You stole our last uniforms.
Thievin' bastards.
See. uh. indigo
grows wild around here.
We use it for blue dye.
That's the color of Virginia.
You boys go’head.
wear all them pretty colors
and get shot first.
I’ll blend into the woods
and die an ol’ man.
What happened
with your grand design?
Royal commission.
Little rich girl.
I buried those plans
when I buried Christopher.
Why'd you come back?
Came back to apologize.
My ambition was selfish.
I owe a debt to
every single one of you.
A debt I cannot repay. but...
When the time comes
for battle. I will be there.
Fighting beside you.
Works for me.
[Henry chuckles]
[low rumbling sound]
[metal clinking]
[David] You need to place
a wager. George.
How about you. uh.
how about you place one for me?
You sure you're all right?
Yeah. never better.
-Thank you.
-Of course.
Excuse me.
Why are y'all here?
We were sent.
By who?
The Fairfaxes.
You'll fight for nobles?
We fight in their stead.
[piano plays softly]
Is that a piano?
Braddock's.
Hauled it all the way
from Alexandria.
I'm sorry.
We're cuttin' a road all the way
through the Ohio territory...
for a piano.
God help us.
[George] One. Two.
Three!
[men groan with effort]
-[David] Tucker!
-[Henry] Watch your feet.
[David] It's gettin'
stuck.
[overlapping chatter]
[David] Keep goin'!
[men groan with
effort]
[George groans in
pain]
[George coughs]
Hey. George.
You sure you're all right?
I'm fine.
Keep pushing. keep pushing.
We're nearly there.
[Braddock] You will acquaint
Mr. Hunter
that His Majesty’s service
requires the further sum
of 10.000 pounds sterling.
[Braddock] How else are we to
deal with the lack of roads
in a wilderness
that is proven formidable?
Did you get that?
Yes. Your Excellency.
Now. where was I?
The siege had been the
longest and the bloodiest...
[warbling voices]
Washington?
oh man. you’re pale as a ghost.
[Braddock muffled]
Washington.
[Braddock]
Washington!
Deliver the dispatch!
Sorry. Your Excellency. I was
lost in your story.
Gist!
[Gage] How is he?
Dysentery.
His case is very severe.
High fever.
terrible nightmares.
He calls out names.
How long will he be down?
Days. a week. forever.
Forever?
He'll survive. won't he?
Washington.
You're awake.
Where are we?
Five miles south of the river.
past the great meadows.
where you fought.
At Necessity. Yes.
I’ve been tasked with a command
of a flying column and 900 men.
We cross the
Monongahela River tomorrow.
The next day we
reach Fort Duquesne.
You should rest.
No!
Look to the trees.
This is a new world.
treat it that way.
Do you not think me
up to the task?
You weren't there.
I question the strategy.
[Nurse] That's enough.
Gage. look to the trees.
I've been preparing
for this all my life. George.
Courage. man.
God please help us.
[dramatic music]
Hold the advance.
[Soldier] Hold the
advance!
advance.
[eerie music plays]
Advance the column.
[Soldier] Advance the
column.
[eerie music continues]
[bird call sound]
Halt!
[Soldier] Halt.
[man] Whoo!
[overlapping chatter]
[gunshot]
Ambush!
[men yelling]
[guns cock]
In line formation.
[Gage] In line
formation!
[men whooping]
Form square!
Form square.
protect the column!
[gunshots impacting]
[men yelling and
whooping]
Number one section.
number two section.
In line formation.
Number one section.
present... fire.
Number two section.
Number one section.
number two section.
To my rear!
Protect the colors!
Get 'em to the river.
-[David] To the river!
-[Henry] To the river!
[inaudible yelling]
[Henry] To the river!
Get 'em to the river.
Come on!
We'll regroup at the river!
[cacophony of yelling
and gunfire]
Retreat!
[horse neighing]
[intense drum beats]
[Braddock] Make ready!
Present...
Fire!
[gunfire]
Build a rank. build a rank!
Build a line!
Move forward!
[gunfire]
Build a rank!
[Braddock] Hold the line!
Hold the line!
[intense. epic music]
[gunfire]
[cannon fire booms]
[gasping]
[cacophony of
gunfire and yelling]
[explosion]
What happened?
We've been ambushed!
From where?
Over the hill!
[gunfire]
[sounds muffle.
gasping as ringing starts]
[grunts with effort]
[gunfire]
[cannon fire]
[epic music]
I wouldn't bother.
Washington.
The battle's lost.
Where's the General?
Ordered a full retreat.
And my men?
You have no men.
The Virginians.
They were at the
front of the line.
It's nearly four
miles from here.
If you go that way.
you will die.
You look like death already.
Listen to me.
You'll never find them.
And even if you did.
you'd never make it back.
[bullet whizzes]
Washington.
Come. my friend.
What could be worth the risk?
[dramatic stinger]
My men.
[epic music]
[explosions thunder]
[soldier grunts]
[cannon booms]
[groans]
[epic music continues]
[Indistinct yelling]
Where is the General?
Where is Braddock?
Hey! Listen to me!
-[bullet whizzes by]
-[horse neighs]
[groans]
Number one section.
Number two section.
Fix bayonets.
[cacophony of gunfire
and screams]
[yelling]
[indistinct yelling]
[groans]
[ominous tones]
[gunshots crack]
Where is the General?
[soldier] He's over
here!
Over here!
General.
[panting]
Washington.
Sir.
You ordered a retreat?
I ordered no retreat.
Rally the men and fall back.
Wear...
Wear this.
They'll know it's mine.
Take my horse and save
as many as you can.
Yes. sir.
I won't let you down.
[dramatic music]
Who would have thought?
[inspiring music]
Retreat!
[booming thuds]
[George] Hold your ground.
there is no retreat.
This way!
There is no retreat.
Fall back! Fall back!
Hold your ground.
there is no retreat!
Hold fast!
Forward!
On me!
[Tucker] George!
Their advance ends here.
We will hold this line.
Fire and move!
Find cover in the trees.
Fire from the trees.
Spread out.
Men this is our land
and we will fight for it.
Independent fire.
Independent fire!
George!
Tucker.
Where are the others?
Where's David?
Where's Henry?
By the river. surrounded.
If they're still alive.
I'm going to try to reach them.
Tucker. rally as many as you can
and move to the river.
Wait for my signal.
I won't let you down. sir.
I'm no officer.
You are the only leader
on this field.
Buy me some time.
You there...
You. you. and you. follow
me. We'll get to the river.
On my command!
[groans]
Make ready.
[horse neighs]
Fire!
[gunshots ring out]
[loud booming thuds]
[men yelling]
[gunshot]
Argh! You damn British guns.
[Sam whimpers]
No. No. No. Sam.
stay with me. son.
Brits left us here to die.
You sound surprised.
[Charles] Sam...
[Henry] How many
rounds left?
My gun doesn't even work. Henry.
[gunshots ringing]
Check for powder.
[horse neighs]
Henry. look.
[Henry] Is that...
[epic music]
It's Washington.
Man's a damn fool.
[grunts]
Come on.
[gunshots]
[grunting]
[yelling]
[gunshot]
-They're behind us.
-[David] Huh?
They flanked you
from the right side.
Well. what do we do?
We fight.
We're all out of power.
Has anybody got powder?
Who has powder?
Here! I got it!
Let's make 'em pay.
Reload every weapon
you can find.
Men of Virginia.
reload your weapons.
To the right. follow me.
Keep that powder on you
and keep it dry.
Let's go. let's go!
Let's give'em hell.
[David] Keep your
head down. Henry.
[grunting]
[George] Virginians. take
cover along the berm!
Keep your heads down.
[cacophony of gunfire
and cannon explosions]
Reload your muskets.
Ahh... you bastard.
Make ready.
Ready?
Present arms!
Fire!
Second rank.
Make ready.
Present arms.
Fire!
On my signal. take the men
as fast as you can to the right.
What are you going to do?
George.
[epic music]
[gunfire]
He's makin’ himself a target.
[epic music]
[speaking Seneca]
[bullets whizzing]
Now!
[Tucker] Present!
Fire!
[Tucker] Freedom!
Independent fire!
[muskets cracking]
Men of Virginia. to the right!
[George] Go! Go!
[triumphant music]
[explosions thunder]
[dramatic music
intensifies]
[distant gunshots]
Only tend to the ones who
you can see breathing.
What is that?
[triumphant music]
[birds chirping]
[triumphant music continues]
What's wrong. sir?
Seen a ghost?
[triumphant music]
There was no order.
What?
To retreat.
The battle was lost. George.
I see no point in
joining him in the grave.
Whose land is this. anyway?
It's our land.
Well. my land is an ocean away.
See. that is the
difference between us.
You all right?
How are the others?
We lost a lot of men.
How many?
Hundreds.
[solemn music]
Thank you for
coming back for us.
Major Washington. the Half-King.
[ominous music]
So. now you fight
for the French?
I no longer fight wars
that are not my own.
Then why are you here?
To find you.
Follow me.
[ominous music
builds]
[speaking Native language]
He wants to know who you are.
Why?
[speaking Native language]
I ordered my
warriors to shoot you.
All of them.
My men never miss.
[speaking Native language]
Our people have a legend.
A spirit of protection that
shields those chosen.
those who walk in destiny.
[speaking Native language]
Creator chose you.
You've been
shielded by the spirit.
[speaking Native language]
So. I ask again.
What are you called?
My name is George Washington.
[speaking Native language]
I will remember this name.
[Dinwiddie] Are those bullet
holes in your jacket?
Apologies.
sir. this is
the only uniform I own--
You misunderstand my statement.
And your hat?
Yes. it's the
only one I own as well.
The militia is in general--
It also has a
bullet hole in it.
How are you alive?
A divine hand. perhaps.
Perhaps.
That says maybe.
But you are
the man of the hour.
That's certain.
Your journals to the council.
they've been published
and have made
you quite well known.
They've even awakened London
to the situation our
colonies now face.
The way you
describe the frontier
has sparked the
imagination of many.
And. um... to your
recent actions.
Mr. Washington's
exemplary courage
was on full display as he evaded
many attacks on his person
while he felled
Indian and French enemies alike.
He also selflessly
rescued hundreds of his men
during a most
impressive retreat.
during which he continued
to battle the enemy with fervor.
despite his infirm condition.
Well. we were defeated.
Sir. 450 lives lost.
another 500 wounded.
But you have won.
Because you endured.
For most. failure is the end.
For you. it seems
only to be the beginning.
And since
leadership is the problem.
I'm going to give you
the opportunity to answer.
A second chance.
We're forming
a Virginia regiment.
1500 men. first of
its kind in the colonies.
and want you to lead it.
I'm reinstating your
rank as Colonel
in the Virginia Regiment.
And Commander
in Chief of all forces
raised in defense
of His Majesty's colony.
Do you accept
this great honor?
Yes. sir. I do.
Well then.
We have much to discuss.
I have...but one request.
Washington. if you ask for equal
pay or a royal commission--
No. sir.
I would like to
discuss the uniform.
Fall in!
Form up on Colonel Washington!
I am not a British officer.
I am not a
gentleman of England.
I have no title.
no royal commission.
But what I do have is you.
All of you.
I am a Virginian.
And it is my
honor to serve you.
To Virginia!
[men] To Virginia!
[men yell and cheer]
To Virginia.
[dramatic music]
Thank you
for being here tonight.
You're not
just watching a film.
you're helping launch a movement
because the ideals
at the heart of this country
still matter.
We believe the story
of George Washington.
of sacrifice. courage.
humility. perseverance.
and faith still matters.
Freedom matters.
virtue matters.
The belief that
liberty is worth fighting for.
that still matters.
So we are inviting
you tonight to Pay it Forward
because when you do.
you give countless families
the chance to see
Young Washington.
and with your help.
Young Washington
can be America's
number one movie.
On the 250th anniversary
of our nation's birth.
we can send a
message loud and clear
that America. and founding
principles that shaped her.
are still worth fighting for.
Thank you so
much for your help.
[dramatic music]
Watch Online Movies and Series for FREE
www.osdb.link/lm